<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The necessity &amp; use of heresies, or, The third and last part of The great question about indifferent things in religious worship containing an answer to the objection against liberty of conscience, from the growth and spreading of heresies / by Edward Bagshaw ...</title>
            <author>Bagshaw, Edward, 1629-1671.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1662</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 60 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A29171</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B419</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R9550</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12532352</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12532352</idno>
            <idno type="VID">62794</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A29171)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 62794)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 304:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The necessity &amp; use of heresies, or, The third and last part of The great question about indifferent things in religious worship containing an answer to the objection against liberty of conscience, from the growth and spreading of heresies / by Edward Bagshaw ...</title>
                  <author>Bagshaw, Edward, 1629-1671.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for S.M. ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1662.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Bagshaw's The great question concerning things indifferent in religious worship" was published in 1660. The second part was published in 1661. Cf. BM.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Heresy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:62794:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE NECESSITY &amp; USE OF HERESIES, Or The Third and Laſt Part OF THE Great Queſtion About <hi>INDIFFERENT THINGS</hi> IN Religious VVorſhip, CONTAINING An Anſwer to the Objection againſt Liberty of Conſcience, from the Growth and Spreading of Hereſies. By <hi>Edward Bagſhaw,</hi> Student of Ch. Church.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>S. M.</hi> at the Star in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-Yard, 1662.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:62794:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:62794:2"/>
            <head>To the Honourable S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> JOHN VAUGHAN Knight of the <hi>Bath,</hi> Second Son to the Right Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, the Earl of <hi>Carberry.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Noble and Learned Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ad I had no other knowledge of your eminent Worth and Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, but what was tranſmitted to me by common fame (which places you, and that deſervedly in the firſt Rank of our moſt knowing and Religious Gentry) that alone would have ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently warranted me in this Addreſſe, ſince thoſe who ſhine like you, in ſo vigorous and active a Sphere of conſtant and unblemiſhed Piety, may eaſily excuſe the careful Beholder, if he turn his body with ſome kind of parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Reſpect &amp; Obſervance towards them. But when to this general Account, which claimes a Reverence from all, there is ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>added an Intention you long have had, to
<pb facs="tcp:62794:3"/>ſhew me ſome perſonal kindneſs (which you have lately performed, with very many Noble and Obliging Circumſtances) I could no longer be juſt, either to my own Reſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Gratitude, or to the Expectation of others, ſhould I not have taken the very firſt Opportunity of manifeſting to the world, how much I think you are to be honoured; and how fit to be propoſed as a Publick Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern. For others of mean Endowments, and narrow Fortunes, to be well principled in vertue, or to take a little compaſs of Learning in their way to Preferment; this carries with it no ſingular commendation, for in ſuch, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity may ſeem to make their choyce for them; but for one in the greateſt outward af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence, &amp; in the midſt of the moſt charming Temptations, both from Honour &amp; Pleaſure, to preſerve an unſpotted integrity, and to keep himſelf free and dis-intereſſed; for the purſuit only of what is truly Great and No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; this is a degree of Excellence, which God vouchſafes to very few: And, Sir, you are one of thoſe, in whoſe manner of Life and Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, we may read, that ſuch kind of rare ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples are not wholly diſcontinued; but God ſhews he hath a Care of this Age alſo, how corrupt ſoever, in that he hath given you, as <hi>Salt,</hi> to ſeaſon it.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:62794:3"/>
            <p>But while others are taken up with admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, what you ſet the loweſt value upon, your accurate Learning, and through Inſight into the profoundeſt depths of Philoſophy, together with a Maſculine and Clean Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, give me leave to take notice of that, which I have often in private Wondred at, your ſtrict and impartial ſearch into the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of Chriſtian Religion, which, while o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers paſs lazily over, or take the belief of them upon truſt, you have made it your bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs ſeverely to examine; and thence have arrived to ſuch an height of Aſſurance, that you can look down upon thoſe Objections &amp; Difficulties, where with puzling Diſputers do trouble both themſelves and others, with a fixed and ſteady eye; and only pity thoſe poor miſtaken <hi>Rationaliſts,</hi> who ſeek for ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, where it is not to be had; like <hi>Saul,</hi> who conſulted with a <hi>Witch,</hi> when none but the Lord could truly anſwer him.</p>
            <p>I cannot therefore wiſh an higher Elogy, to this ſmall Treatiſe, then that it were as fit for your view, as you are able to judge of it; For you, Sir, are experimentally acquainted with the Truth it contains; and can demonſtrate from the moſt undoubted Teſtimony, that God hath a little number in the world,
<pb facs="tcp:62794:4"/>whom in ſpite of <hi>Hell</hi> or <hi>Hereſies,</hi> he is reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to ſave; and therefore by ſtate-Arts and Politick Contrivances, to labour the Preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Hereſies,</hi> it is as to the <hi>Elect,</hi> a <hi>needleſs,</hi> as to <hi>Reprobates</hi> an <hi>unprofitable care,</hi> and <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warrantable</hi> to both, ſince, when the Scripture tels us, <hi>there muſt be Hereſies;</hi> they only take the way to perpetuate them, who endeavour their ſuppreſſion, by waies which that Word hath not warranted. As winds, till they are pent up &amp; reſtrained from their motion, do ſeldom any hurt; ſo nor <hi>Hereſies</hi> neither, till they are impoſed and forced, they make no publick diſturbance. The world would never have been <hi>Arian</hi> heretofore, nor <hi>Antichriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> now, did not Princes lend their Power <hi>to the Beaſt,</hi> to make it kill, whom it cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute. That all mens Eyes may be opened to ſee that Chriſtian Religion, which is the <hi>Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of God,</hi> needs not any Aſſiſtance from the undue <hi>Power of man,</hi> and that you, whoſe eies are already opened, may be long Preſerved for the Information and Example of others, is, and ſhall be the conſtant Prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Drury Lane,</hi> 
                  <date>Jan. 10, 1661.</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>NOBLE SIR,</salute>
               <signed>Your truly Affectionate and most Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged Servant, Edward Bagſhaw.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:62794:4"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mong all the Arguments, which are made uſe of in defence of a rigorous and ſtated Uniformity, againſt the pretenſions and Plea of <hi>Chriſtian Liberty,</hi> there is none, that is either urged with greater vigour, or that, amongſt unwary and ſuperficial Hearers, carries with it a better appearance of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability, then this, that the Impoſing of ſome few things, ſuppoſed to be <hi>Indifferent,</hi> is the only way to prevent the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance, and to ſuppreſs the growth of <hi>Hereſies.</hi> For as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruly Cattel are kept from ſtraying, by being put into a Pound, or into ſome ſtraight Encloſure, ſo, where there is a certain <hi>Form,</hi> and fixed <hi>Garb</hi> of <hi>Worſhip,</hi> unto which all are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled to agree; there will in all probability, be no room left, for thoſe ſecret underminings, and clardeſtine Inſinuations, by which, Errour, like undiſcovered fire, is blown up and kindled, and ſpreads it ſelf, to the ruine ſomtimes both of <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State.</hi> And therefore as they tell us, that <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurers,</hi> to keep their evil Spirits from doing miſchief, do draw a <hi>Circle</hi> about them, and confine them to it; ſo, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrates, who are the <hi>State-Exorciſts,</hi> have no better way to prevent the Deſigns of Factious and light ſpirited men, (who oftentimes cry up <hi>Religion,</hi> when they mean <hi>Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion</hi>) then to confine all, even <hi>Religious Meetings,</hi> unto ſuch a <hi>Circle</hi> and <hi>Order,</hi> out of which, they may not be ſuffered to move, leſt Conſcience, which ſeems at firſt to ſtart and
<pb facs="tcp:62794:5"/>ſcruple at ſmall things, becomes at length, for want of due Bounds, a Patronage and Plea for the greateſt and moſt ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regular Exorbitancies.</p>
            <p>That I may take nothing from the strength of this Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (which may be yet farther improved by conſideration of the great <hi>Scandal</hi> given in our own time) I will confeſs, that were a State, which profeſſeth to embrace <hi>Chriſtian Religion,</hi> not ſolely to be guided according to the Rules of that, but left at random, to be governed by thoſe <hi>Prudential Motives,</hi> and <hi>Political Maximes,</hi> which the <hi>Wiſdom of this World</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> that the Apoſtle cals <hi>earthly, ſenſual and deviliſh</hi> is most ready to invent and to faſten upon; there ſeems nothing, at firſt Bluſh, to be ſo contrary to <hi>Reaſon of State,</hi> as a <hi>Toleration</hi> of two or more Religions, or the leaſt variation in the <hi>Mode</hi> and <hi>Form</hi> of <hi>Publick Worſhip;</hi> ſince this Diverſity, may eaſily be preſumed to beget Diſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Quarrels, which ariſing at firſt in private Families, like wind that lies concealed in ſecret Caverns, at laſt breaks out into an Earthquake, and, like a mighty Tempeſt, over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turnes and bears down all before it.</p>
            <p>It is, I believe, upon ſome ſuch fallacious and ill weighed Inducement, as this I mention, that there hath been a kind of Conſpiracy, amongſt all <hi>worldly wiſe</hi> and <hi>ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>political</hi> men, against the ſincere, ſpiritual and unmixed Profeſſion of Chriſtianity, ever ſince the death and murder of him, from whom it received both its Name and Doctrine. For we read that Chriſt ſuffered as a <hi>Diſturber</hi> of that ſtate, which he came to ſave; and as a <hi>Blaſphemous Heretick,</hi> in that Church, which he came to teach. <hi>Paul,</hi> and the reſt of the Apoſtles met with the very ſame entertainment, both for Language and Uſage; and afterwards, for <hi>300</hi> years toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, all kind of violence was practiſed againſt the <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> as <hi>State-Incendiaries,</hi> and men that were obstinate
<pb facs="tcp:62794:5"/>only in Impious and Seditious Errours. But our Religion loſt moſe by <hi>Peace,</hi> then by that bloudy and outragious <hi>War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare;</hi> all the while the Ship of the <hi>True Church</hi> rode out at Sea, the Storms it met with, did only toſs but could not overwhelm it; In a <hi>Calm,</hi> it began to ſink, and never was near periſhing, till it came to Harbour. In ſhort, the Profeſſed Favourers of <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> did, by their well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meant, but ill managed kindneſs, more deſtroy the <hi>Church,</hi> then all its open and moſt furious Enemies. For when <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine</hi> and his Succeſſors, miſtaking quite the Nature of our Religion, did labour to accommodate and attemper it unto their <hi>Civil Inter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> ſtraight the old Heatheniſh Spirit of <hi>Idolatry and Perſecution,</hi> did revive, under new Names; and <hi>Hereticks,</hi> i.e. Diſſenters from the eſtabliſhed Forms then, were as ſeverely handled, as <hi>Chriſtians</hi> themſelves before. Which courſe was ſo long continued, until <hi>Policy</hi> and <hi>Pomp</hi> had quite devoured and eaten out the <hi>Purity</hi> and <hi>Plamneſs</hi> of Religion, and made it nothing elſe but a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty, for ambitious <hi>Church-men</hi> (who in all Ages, have been the greateſt Cryers up of, becauſe the only Gainers by, a <hi>Specious Uniformity,</hi> of which they are the ſole Managers) to make Attempts upon the <hi>Civil Power;</hi> which at laſt, they wreſted out of the Emperours hands, and in token of their entire Conqueſt, they depoſed not <hi>Princes</hi> only, but <hi>Scripture</hi> &amp; <hi>Reaſon,</hi> &amp; the <hi>Spirit</hi> of God himſelf too from their Authority; and ſet up a <hi>Political Head</hi> of their own, unto whoſe pretended <hi>infallible</hi> Dictates they enforced all to yield an <hi>abſolute,</hi> becauſe <hi>blind</hi> and <hi>ignorant</hi> Obedience. Thus, under colour of ſuppreſſing <hi>Hereſies,</hi> the world con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to enſlave themſelves unto the most <hi>damnable,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive and fatal <hi>Hereſie,</hi> that ever the Sun ſaw; I mean, to <hi>Popery;</hi> which, by a ſtrange kind of Figure, would paſs for the only <hi>Chriſtian Religion,</hi> when as it hath in it just no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb facs="tcp:62794:6"/>of the <hi>Spirit, Purity, Knowledge,</hi> or <hi>Liberty</hi> that <hi>Chriſt</hi> eſtabliſhed. In which ſad condition the greateſt part of the Chriſtian world yet lies, and groans, for the ſpeedy Coming of its <hi>Redeemer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This having been the ſucceſs and iſſue of <hi>Uniformity,</hi> and this being its natural Tendency, I wiſh all ſerious and diſpaſſionate Chriſtians would conſider, that, though <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies</hi> are to be bewailed, and ſo far as we lawfully can, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed too, yet we muſt do <hi>Bonum bene.</hi> We muſt not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy an Inconvenience, with bringing in a Miſchief; nor deviſe expedients of a ſtrict and violent <hi>Uniformity,</hi> which as God in his Word hath no where warranted, ſo, we may find by the ſucceſs of it among the <hi>Papiſts</hi> and others, that he hath not bleſſed. Since by this means, quite contrary to Gods Command, many Millions of Soules are forced to ſit down under a wretched and irreparable Ignorance; their over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>careful Guides, for fear it ſeems, leſt they ſhould loſe their way to Heaven, having with a great deal of Caution, taken their Candle from them.</p>
            <p>How unfit I am to be, ſo much as inſtrumental, in <hi>pulling off the Vaile</hi> from before mens eyes, I deſire to be alwaies ſenſible: yet having already ventured upon this Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, I have here once more tried to rectiſie mens mistakes; &amp; laboured to take away the ſtrength of that Objection againſt due <hi>Chriſtian Liberty,</hi> from the many Hereſies, which thereby are occaſioned. In this ſhort Treatiſe therefore, I have endeavoured to manifeſt, that, <hi>in the Church of Chriſt, there muſt be Hereſies.</hi> And while we obſerve that dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence and care in our ſelves, together with that equity and moderation towards others, which our Religion doth require from us, it is as impoſſible to avoid <hi>Diverſity of Opinions</hi> (which among angry men, will certainly enough be nick-na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Hereſies</hi>) as it would be to place our ſelves in the midſt
<pb facs="tcp:62794:6"/>of Sun-ſhine, and not ſee Variety of Colours. Mens Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, eſpecially if they give themſelves any Latitude of Enquiry, are as various as their Complexions; ſo that to preſcribe one certain Form to all, and thereby to force men to act outwardly, what inwardly they do not aſſent to, is like Painting the Face with an infectious and Venomous Juice, or giving a Nauſeous Potion unto a Nice and Dainty Palat, whereby we ſhall offend God, as much as men; who at the last day, will not thank any, for other mens conſtrained, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voluntary, and therefore falſe and <hi>hypocritical</hi> Devotion.</p>
            <p>Having ſaid thus much, I now take my leave of this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie; not as if I thought, that more could not be written, but becauſe I am no longer in a free capacity to do it: Since I cannot write now in ſo unconcerned a manner as I did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. For having lately been deprived of my juſt Right, in a Freehold I had at <hi>Ch. Church,</hi> for no reaſon at all, that I know of, unleſs for the impartial and unbyaſsed Diſcovery of my Judgment about <hi>Indifferent,</hi> or rather <hi>Doubtful Things in Religious Worſhip:</hi> It will but wrong the cauſe; ſhould I proſecute it any further; ſince it may be interpreted now, that I write like a <hi>Party;</hi> and that, not Conſcience, but Diſcontent doth excite me to it. Unleſs therefore I am called out to defend what I have already written, I ſhall for the future forbear; and manifeſt by my carriage, that though for the preſent, I cannot <hi>ſubmit,</hi> yet, I thank God, I can <hi>ſuffer</hi> in ſilence.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Drury Lane. <date>
                     <hi>Jan. 10. 1661.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>EDWARD BAGSHAW.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:62794:7"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:62794:7"/>
            <head>THE NECESSITY and USE OF HERESIES.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1 Cor. 11.19.</hi>
                  </bibl> For there must alſo be Hereſies among you, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe are the Words of the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> and urged by him as a Reaſon, why he did believe the Report he had heard concerning their <hi>Schiſmes</hi> and <hi>Contentions;</hi> For as we find, <hi>Chap.</hi> 1. He tels them, <note place="margin">Verſe 11.</note>that he was informed by ſome who were related to the Family of <hi>Chloe</hi> (who ſeems to have been a Woman of Quality and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute in that Church of <hi>Corinth</hi>) that there were <hi>Contentions among them:</hi> Each Party endeavouring to cry up thoſe Teachers by whom they were firſt converted, or moſt profited, to the Preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice and Diſgrace of the reſt: Whereupon, one ſaid, <note place="margin">Verſe 12.</note>he was of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:62794:8"/>
               <hi>Paul; i. e.</hi> a Diſciple of <hi>Paul;</hi> another was for <hi>Peter;</hi> a third ſort for <hi>Apollos;</hi> whereby they did not ſo much bandy againſt one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, as oppoſe the Honour of the Lord <hi>Chriſt;</hi> who, by theſe Miniſters, as his Inſtruments, did work their Salvation. And therefore for them, to have ſuch fierce and vehement Conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, about thoſe who were meerly ſubordinate, and could do nothing but as the Power of <hi>Chriſt</hi> did co-operate with them, ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gued theſe <hi>Corinthians,</hi> notwithſtanding their <hi>Gifts,</hi> to be very raw,
<note place="margin">V. 4, 7.</note> childiſh, and carnal Chriſtians: As the Apoſtle concludes, <hi>Chap.</hi> 3. <hi>For-while one ſaith, I am of Paul, and another, I am of Apollos, are not ye carnal? i. e.</hi> Are ye not led by very weak and childiſh Inclinations, to make ſuch a Note of Difference among your ſelves, becauſe of your Teachers?) <hi>For who is Paul? and who is Apollos, but Miniſters, by whom (i. e.</hi> by whoſe Miniſtry, and Preaching) <hi>ye believed, even as the Lord gave to every man? (i. e.</hi> according to that ability which God was pleaſed to diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to each of his Miniſters) to him therefore the ſole Honour is due, and not to be factiouſly aſcribed to any of his Servants; as the Apoſtle further argues, <hi>I have planted, i. e.</hi> laid amongſt you the Foundation of Chriſtian Faith; <hi>Apollos hath wateved i.e.</hi> by his Eloquence (for we read that he was <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <note place="margin">Acts 18.25.</note> 
               <hi>i. e. a well spoken man) Apollos</hi> hath added a Verdure and Freſhneſs to my Doctrine, and made it ſpring up amongſt you: <hi>But,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>God gave the increaſe, i. e.</hi> made it fruitful and effectual. From whence it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, that <hi>neither he that planteth is any thing, i. e.</hi> to be eſteemed, and ſolely gloried in; <hi>nor he that watereth, but God who giveth the increaſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having thus convinced them of their Folly, as well as ſin, in making <hi>Schiſmes</hi> upon ſuch ill-grounded pretences; he proceeds in this Chapter, to take notice of a great Diſorder, which they committed even at the time of the Sacrament; for there, when they ſhould have acted in the higheſt Love and Coudeſcention towards each other, yet then they brought their Contentions and Animoſities along with them, and made the <hi>Publick Aſſembly,</hi> (for ſo I underſtand the Word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſince the Chriſtians as yet had no publick Places of Reſort, but met, as they could, in Private Houſes) witneſſes of their unchriſtian Diſcord. <hi>When ye come together in the Church,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>i. e.</hi> as Iunderſtand it, <hi>in the Rublick Aſſembly, I hear that there be Diviſions among you:</hi> and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:62794:8"/>though it might ſeem a thing almoſt impoſſible, at that time, when you come to receive the <hi>Lords Supper,</hi> and in that Place, when all the Faithful are met together, there ſhould be any ſo bold Defyers of Chriſtian <hi>Charity</hi> and <hi>Order,</hi> as then and there, to vent their Diſcontents, and manifeſt an ambitious Strife; <hi>yet,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>I partly believe it; For there muſt alſo be Hereſies amongſt you,</hi> &amp;c. And therefore I do not much wonder if you begin ſo early in <hi>Schiſm</hi> and <hi>Separation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The words contain Two Parts. 1. A Prediction. <hi>There muſt be Hereſies.</hi> 2. One Reaſon or Ground of it. That <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>i. e. thoſe that are approved and ſincere, may be made manifeſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
               </label> The Poſition or Doctrine that I intend to inſiſt on, is, That <hi>in the Church of Chriſt, there is an unavoidable neceſſity of hereſies.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 17.1.</note> As our Saviour ſaith of <hi>Offences,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>i. e. It is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanceable,</hi> or, <hi>it cannot happen but they muſt come.</hi> So ſay I of <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, It is impoſſible to avoid it, but they will come.</p>
            <p>To clear up this, I ſhall explain theſe two things. 1. What is meant by <hi>Hereſies.</hi> 2. What are the Grounds or Reaſons, why in the Church of Chriſt, they are ſo fatally neceſſary.</p>
            <p>For the Firſt, <hi>viz.</hi> What is <hi>Hereſie?</hi> Some hold it is impoſſible to be defined, amongſt whom was <hi>Auſtin.</hi> Others define it to be <hi>Sententia humano ſenſu electa, Scripturae Sacrae contraria, palam edo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cta, &amp; pertinaciter defenſa,</hi> i. e.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat. Pariſ.</hi> p. 874.</note> 
               <hi>An Opinion choſen by a mans own Underſtanding, contrary to the holy Scriptures, openly taught, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinately defended.</hi> Which is the Deſinition of <hi>Groſthead,</hi> the Learned Biſhop of <hi>Lincolne,</hi> who for his ſingular Zeal in oppoſing the Popes Uſurpations in <hi>England,</hi> was ſtiled, <hi>Romanorum Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leus &amp; Contemptor.</hi> With this Deſinition, becauſe of the Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Vertue of its Author, I ſhould acquieſce, but that all who have got long poſſeſſion of any Tenet, charge Diſſenters with the name of <hi>Hereticks;</hi> and every one, who maintains any ſingular Opinion, doth endeavour to back it with Authority of Scripture. And therefore without attending to Concluſions of others, the beſt way to underſtand aright the nature and meaning of <hi>Hereſie,</hi> will be to have recourſe our ſelves unto the Scripture, from whence alone we had the firſt Notice of ſuch a thing; I mean, as it is a thing criminal and damnable.</p>
            <p>In the Scripture I find the word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to be <hi>vox mediae ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cationis,</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:62794:9"/>and to ſignifie any <hi>Opinion</hi> indifferently, whether <hi>good</hi> or <hi>bad.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 15.17.</note> Thus we read of the <hi>hereſie of the Sadduces;</hi> and the <hi>hereſie of the Phariſees.</hi> And <hi>Paul</hi> mentions it of himſelf, by way of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour:
<note place="margin">Acts 15.5. Acts 26.5.</note> according to the <hi>moſt exact or accurate hereſie or Opinion of our Religion, I lived a Phariſee.</hi> But for the moſt part, the word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is taken in an ill ſenſe, to ſignifie, an <hi>Opinion repugnant to the ſenſe of Scripture, and likewiſe deſtructive of the Civil Peace.</hi> Thus when <hi>Tertullus</hi> would blaſt the Repute of Chriſtian Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on before <hi>Felix,</hi> the Roman Deputy, he cals it an <hi>hereſie: We have,</hi> ſaith he,
<note place="margin">Acts 24 5.</note> ſpeaking in behalf of the <hi>Jews</hi> againſt <hi>Paul, found this man</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>a very Peſt, and one that moveth</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Sedition,</hi> or <hi>up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roar amongſt the Jews, throughout the world; and a chief Leader of the Sect</hi> or <hi>Hereſie of the Nazarenes:</hi> So doth he in contempt call the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> as being the followers of <hi>Jeſus of Nazareth,</hi> which was a Name of Diſgrace and Obloquy among them. As <hi>Paul</hi> te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifies of himſelf, whilſt he was yet an Unbeliever; <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>I thought with my ſelf,
<note place="margin">Acts 26.9.</note> that I ought to do many things againſt the Name of Jeſus of Nazareth.</hi> In this ſenſe is the word <hi>Hereſies</hi> to be underſtood,
<note place="margin">Gal. 5.20, 21.</note> when by the Apoſtle they are reckoned among <hi>Works of the Fleſh,</hi> and they are joyned with <hi>Strife, Seditions, Wrath, Envyings,</hi> which are the uſual Attendants of <hi>Hereſie.</hi> Now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>Works of the fleſh</hi> are of two ſorts, either ſuch as flow from the <hi>fleſhly Underſtanding</hi> (as the Apoſtle cals corrupt Reaſon, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the <hi>Underſtanding of the Fleſh</hi>) or ſuch as flow from the <hi>fleſhly Will;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Col. 2.18.</note> accordingly there are two ſorts of <hi>hereſies</hi> mentioned and ſpoken againſt in Scripture. 1. Such as upon Preſumptions of <hi>natural Reaſon,</hi> do contradict expreſs and clear Revelation of Scripture.
<note place="margin">2 Pet. 2.1.</note> Thus the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> cals the <hi>denying our Lord Chriſt, i. e.</hi> either his Nature, as the <hi>Socinians</hi> of our times; or his <hi>Offices,</hi> as all the <hi>Papiſts do,</hi> a <hi>damnable Hereſie. There ſhall,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>be falſe Teachers among you, who</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ſhall covertly,</hi> (or <hi>over and above,</hi> or <hi>contrary to the Truth) bring in deſtructive hereſies, even denying the Lord that bought them.</hi> So the Opinion of thoſe, who under pretence of <hi>Humility,</hi> brought in the <hi>Worſhip of Angels,</hi> into the Church of <hi>Coloſſe,</hi> was a Formal <hi>hereſie,</hi> ſince the Authors of it, had no warrant of Scripture to add ſuch kind of <hi>Party Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ators</hi> to Chriſt,
<note place="margin">Col. 2.18.</note> but as the Apoſtle ſpeaks, <hi>were raſhly puffed up by their fleſhly mind.</hi> Thus the <hi>denying of the Reſurrection of the Body,</hi> by ſome in the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> was a great <hi>Hereſie,</hi> as over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwing
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:62794:9"/>the Foundation of a Chriſtians hope,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.12.</note> and opening a door to all manner of Impiety and Villany; <hi>For if the dead riſe not,</hi> the Conſequence is very natural and reaſonable, <hi>let us eat and drink, for to morrow we ſhall die</hi> 2. <note place="margin">Verſe 32.</note>There are another ſort of He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies ſpoken againſt in Scripture, which flow from the <hi>fleſhly will,</hi> and have an immediate tendency to patronize and encourage diſſoluteneſs of Liſe, ſuch was the Hereſie of the <hi>Nicolaitans,</hi> who held, that it was lawful to <hi>eat things offered to Idols, i. e.</hi> to commit I olatry, in times of Perſecution; and to <hi>commit Fornication,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Apoc. 3, 14, 15.</note> which our Saviour ſpeaks ſharply againſt in the <hi>Revelations,</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling it the <hi>Doctrine of Balaam,</hi> and expreſſeth his utter diſlike of ſuch Tenets, in theſe words, <hi>which I hate.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Pot. 2.</note> So the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaks againſt ſome vicious <hi>Hereticks</hi> (as ſome think, the <hi>Gno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticks</hi>) who, under pretence of advancing <hi>Chriſtian Liberty,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Verſe 19.</note>gave themſelves up to all manner of Impurity; <hi>promiſing,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, they themſelves are the Servants of Corruption.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jude <hi>v</hi> 8.</note> 
               <hi>Jude</hi> carries on the ſame mens <hi>hereſie</hi> further, and ſaith, they did not only, <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>file the fleſh,</hi> but by ſtretching the Notion of <hi>Liberty,</hi> beyond its due Bounds, did ſet at nought <hi>Government, and revile Dignities, i. e.</hi> undervalue, diſeſteem, and diſobey their Civil Governours. Which kind of Hereſies, as they are more dangerous, ſo they are more damnable then others; becauſe there can be no pretence of Conſcience to juſtifie them. From what I have ſaid concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>Hereſies,</hi> as I find them recorded in Scripture, I draw this ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Definition of them all. An <hi>Hereſie is ſuch an Opinion, as either hath no Foundation in Scripture,</hi> (as the <hi>Worſhip of Angels,</hi> among the <hi>Coloſſians</hi>) or, <hi>expreſly contradicts it</hi> (as <hi>the denial of the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection,</hi> among the <hi>Corinthians</hi>) or, <hi>Miſtakes and miſſe-interprets it, to countenance diſſoluteneſs of Life, and diſobedience unto the Civil Magiſtrate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The neceſſity that there ſhould be ſuch <hi>hereſies</hi> in the Church of Chriſt, will appear, from the conſideration, 1. Of the <hi>Cauſes.</hi> 2. Of the <hi>Occaſions,</hi> which concur to the producing of them.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Neceſſity of <hi>Hereſies</hi> will appear from the conſideration of their Cauſes, and they are theſe three, 1. <hi>God permitting.</hi> 2. <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan exciting.</hi> 3. <hi>Man begetting and ingendring of them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Cauſe. </seg>1</label> 1. The firſt Cauſe of <hi>Hereſies,</hi> which makes the being of them <hi>neceſſary,</hi> is, <hi>Gods permiſſion of them.</hi> Where, by <hi>Permiſſion,</hi> I do not mean, an idle, unconcerned, ineffectual letting them paſſe
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:62794:10"/>only, and barely ſuffering them to be; but Gods wiſe, powerful, and mighty ordering of them, as he did the <hi>hardneſs of Pharaohs heart,</hi> for very gracious and holy ends, eſpecially theſe two.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>For the Trial of the Godly:</hi> As the Apoſtle hath it, that the <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the ſincere and ſingle-hearted Chriſtians,</hi> might, by this means, appear the more eminent and conſpicuous. As it did ſhew the Power of God, to preſerve the <hi>Buſh</hi> (by which his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Iſrael</hi> was repreſented) <hi>in the midſt of the Fire;</hi> ſo doth his Power equally appear, when his Truth is born witneſs to, in the midſt of the Triumph and Efficacy of Errour. Were there but one Opinion which paſſed for currant among Chriſtians, there would not appear any thing extraordinary in the owning of it; but when there are ſo many Parties, each crying up their own way, as the <hi>Epheſians</hi> did their <hi>Diana,</hi> there to keep touch with the <hi>things of God,</hi> and, in ſpight of all contradiction, openly to avow and countenance them, this ſhews a well-principled Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity; a temper that God is ſingularly delighted with. In the world, God lets his Heaven be oftentimes wrapped up in clouds, that the ſtars which he hath appointed for the Government of the Night,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vid.</hi> Deut. 13.1, 3.</note> may appear more bright and uſeful: So in the <hi>Church,</hi> which is Gods Heaven on Earth, the moſt viſible Manſion of the Divine Nature, he lets Darkneſs break forth, and thick Vapours; that thoſe Saints of his, whom he cals <hi>Lights of the world,</hi> may ſhine with the greater Luſtre, and redouble their Beams, from the greatneſs of the Oppoſition made againſt them. We muſt not think that God hath either given us <hi>Faith</hi> or <hi>Knowledge,</hi> which are his choiceſt Largeſſes, but he intends to try the conſtancy of the one, and the ſeriouſneſs of the other: And ſince the greater Difficulties we encounter, ſtill the more Honour redounds to God, who is our General; therefore he will ſeem to hazard his Truth, by letting it, to outward appearance, be loſt as it were, in the midſt of a ſwarm of <hi>Hereſies,</hi> that by raiſing up ſome <hi>Heroick Champions,</hi> he may recover it again with greater advantage. Thus in the firſt ages of the Church, <hi>Peter</hi> reſcued Freedom of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with the Gentiles; <hi>Paul</hi> aſſerts Freedom from the <hi>Yoke</hi> of needleſs and inſignificant Ceremonies; and <hi>John</hi> defended the Eternal Divinity of our Saviour, againſt the Narrow-ſpirited, Tyrannical, and Helliſh Impoſtures of the Hereticks in their Times: And in all ages, many there are recorded to us of great
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:62794:10"/>eſteem and credit in the Church of Chriſt, whoſe Memories, in all probability, had not ſurvived their Bodies, had not they ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalized themſelves by their zealous aſſerting of Truth, when it was almoſt ſwallowed up by the Deluge, or outfaced by the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of Errour. And ſuch Examples God will ever continue; for which Reaſon, he lets <hi>Hereſie,</hi> like <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and his <hi>Egyptians,</hi> captivate his Truth, that he may ſend ſome <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aarons</hi> for the Redemption and Deliverance of it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Second, and no leſs principal end,
<note place="margin">Ezek. 3.20.</note> as to the Deſign of God, why he permits <hi>Hereſies,</hi> is, that <hi>Reprobates may have occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions preſented them of ſtumbling and taking Offence.</hi> When a wicked man turns from that <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> he once pretended to, God ſaies, <hi>I lay a ſtumbling block before him;</hi> and upon the wicked, the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> ſaies, <hi>God raines Snares, i. e.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 11.6.</note> ſcatters Traps and Snares in their way, that they may be taken. There are ſome men, who in Scripture are ſtiled, <hi>the People of Gods curſe, the Veſſels of his wrath,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 34.5. Rom. 9.21. Jude <hi>v.</hi> 4.</note> and by <hi>Jude, Forewritten unto condemnation:</hi> To whom Gods great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt methods of Goodneſs prove only means of hardning them, to ſin more deſperately; thus did Gods Word prove to the <hi>Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites: It was,</hi> ſaith the Prophet, <hi>Line upon Line,
<note place="margin">Iſa. 2.8, 13.</note> and Precept upon Precept, that they might go, and fall backward, and be broken, and ſnared, and taken.</hi> And <hi>Christ,</hi> to the unbelieving <hi>Jews,</hi> became a <hi>Sione of ſtumbling, and a Rock of Offence, unto which,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.8.</note> ſaith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle <hi>Peter, they were appointed.</hi> So the Goſpel, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>to loſt,</hi> and <hi>periſhing Wretches, is a Savour of death.</hi> But what theſe things do only by accident, that <hi>Hereſies</hi> do in their own proper nature,
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 2.15.</note> 
               <hi>i. e.</hi> they harden Unbelievers, and make them more reſolute in their oppoſing of the Truth. As when God did intend <hi>Ahab</hi> ſhould go down to battel, and periſh there,
<note place="margin">1 Kings 22.22.</note> he let a <hi>Lying Spirit of Propheſie</hi> be in the mouth of all his Prophets; <hi>For,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>thou ſhalt perſwade him, and prevail alſo.</hi> So when God ſees a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of lazy, vicious men, who are weary of the Powerful plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Truth, then he lets ſome <hi>corrupt Doctrines</hi> be ſcattered a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, which may fit thoſe Inclinations, they are already princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled with: and likewiſe, when others have <hi>curious itching Ears,</hi> and <hi>ſound Doctrine</hi> will not relliſh with them, then God ſuffers ſome lofty airy ſpeculations to be broached, by ſtudy of which, they may grow drunk with Pride and Prejudice againſt more wholſom Tenets.
<note place="margin">2 Theſ. 2.10, 12.</note> It was this juſt Judgment of God upon mens
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:62794:11"/>willingneſs to be deceived, that God gave them up to Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, <hi>i.e.</hi> to <hi>Papal</hi> Deluſions. As the Apoſtle hath it, <hi>Becauſe they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived not the Love of the Truth, that they might be ſaved. For this cauſe God ſhall ſend them</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the active power and efficacy of Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour,
<note place="margin">Mat. 18.</note> that they ſhould believe a lie, i.e.</hi> a falſe and feigned doctrine. <hi>That they all may be damned who have not believed the Truth, but had pleaſure in unrighteouſneſs, i.e.</hi> in falſe and unrighteous Tenets. And therefore as our Saviour ſayes, <hi>Wo to the world, becauſe of Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences;</hi> ſo, <hi>Wo to the world, becauſe of Hereſies;</hi> becauſe as we ſet traps to catch Vermine, ſo God appoints theſe to enſnare arrogant and ſelf-preſuming, or vicious and ſelf-defiling men.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Cauſe. </seg>2</label> 2. The ſecond Cauſe which concurs to the producing of <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies,</hi> is <hi>Satan exciting.</hi> That <hi>evil Spirit,</hi> whom our Saviour cals, <hi>the Prince of the world,</hi> and the Apoſtle, <hi>the ruler of the Darkneſs of the world;</hi> out of that innate hatred he hath to Truth, by which his Kingdom is overthrown, ſcatters the ſeeds of Errour and ignorance, every where up and down the world: and as he ſet upon our Saviour with miſſe quoted Scripture, in which he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared ſo dexterous and ready, as if he intended to puzzle and non-plus his eternal wiſdom: So the moſt deadly and poyſonous <hi>hereſies,</hi> have by him, by a ſtrange kind of Chymiſtry, been extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted out of the ſame holy Scriptures. Thus he brought in the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of needleſs rigour and auſterity of Life,
<note place="margin">Col. 2.</note> under pretence of Chriſtian ſtrictneſs and ſeverity, in thoſe Precepts, <hi>Touch not, taſt not,
<note place="margin">1 Tim. 4.</note> handle not.</hi> Thus brought he in the Doctrine of <hi>forbidding mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages,</hi> under pretence of Chriſtian Chaſtity and Abſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence,
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 11.3.</note> which the Apoſtle in expreſs words, cals the <hi>Doctrine of Devils.</hi> Thus he brought in <hi>Superſtition, Will-worſhip,</hi> and <hi>idle Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies,</hi> under pretence of Chriſtian <hi>Decency and Order;</hi> thereby, as the Apoſtle complains, <hi>the Serpent beguiling many through his Subtilty,
<note place="margin">Rev. 13.</note> ſo that their minds were corrupted from the ſimplicity which was in Chriſt.</hi> Thus laſtly, brought he in the cruel and incompaſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate killing of men that would not <hi>worſhip the Image of the Beaſt,</hi> and in ſome outward and viſible manner acknowledge their. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity, under pretence of Chriſtian zeal and care of Truth. In ſhort, as the greateſt Cordials, if not rightly prepared, do prove the moſt deadly and killing Poyſons; ſo the moſt dangerous and deſtructive hereſies, have been compounded by <hi>Satans</hi> malice, out of the moſt Soveraign Drugs of Sacred Truth; but by him pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely ill mixed and tempered. And here I deſire to obſerve,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:62794:11"/>that though the Devil likewiſe doth ſtir up <hi>Perſecution,</hi> as our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour felt in himſelf, when he ſaid of his own Sufferings, that then was the <hi>Power of darkneſs, i.e.</hi> Hell was then broke looſe,
<note place="margin">Luke 22.53.</note> and wicked men in crucifying Chriſt, acted the Devils buſineſſes; ſo he foretels to the Church of <hi>Smyrna, Fear none of thoſe things thou art to ſuffer; behold the Devil ſhall caſt ſome of you into priſon,
<note place="margin">Rev. 3.10.</note> that you may be tried.</hi> Yet this is but Satans After-game; for his great deſign is, to eclipſe the beauty of Truth, by the Miſt of Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour: And if he finds, that his <hi>Heretical Tares</hi> will not take root, then under pretence of <hi>Faction; Sedition,</hi> and the like old charges, which were laid both againſt our Saviour, and his Apoſtles, he deſtroyes thoſe careful Husbandmen; which would ſow better Seed, and leave no room for the Devils Cockle. The Art and Policy of Hell, lies in the quiet ſpreading of <hi>Hereſie,</hi> for this gains him ſouls, whereas violence never got him any thing, but the bodies of men; that is, it made them <hi>obſequious Slaves,</hi> but not <hi>real Converts.</hi> WE find therefore in the <hi>Revelation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 12.</note> that when the Woman, under which the True Church is emblemed, <hi>had brought forth, the Divel stood by, ready to devour her Child as ſoon as it was born;</hi> and for ſome time, endeavoured to maintain his foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Heaven, and till he was caſt down from thence, did not think of <hi>making war with her Seed.</hi> The Moral of which Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentation, I take to be this, That when Chriſtian Truth begins to break forth, then the Devil for a time endeavours to deſtroy it, by diſputing the caſe, and venturing his cauſe upon Argument; but when he finds himſelf maſtered at that weapon, then he changes the <hi>Subtilty of the Serpent,</hi> into the <hi>Roaring of the Lion;</hi> and with open mouth devours his Oppoſers. But this way the Devil doth not ordinarily try, till his <hi>Falſe Doctrines</hi> have been baffled and foyled, and he hath no <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, no <hi>Wile,</hi> no <hi>craft</hi> left, to countenance the groſſeneſs of his Impoſtures.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Cauſe </seg>3</label> 3. The third Cauſe concurring to the neceſſary Being of <hi>here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies</hi> in the Church, is, <hi>Man himſelf, begetting and ingendring of them.</hi> For as the moſt fruitful and pregnant Seed, if it be not caſt into a warm and prepared Soyl, ſoſeth all its Vertue, ſo thoſe Seeds of Errour the Devil ſowes, if the heart of man was not a fit ſoyl for them, would never riſe up again in ſo large an harveſt of abſurd and impious Hereſies. Were the winds never ſo fierce, yet if the water of the Sea were not of an unſtable and moveable
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:62794:12"/>nature, there would never be any Tempeſt. So, how impetuous and violent ſoever the Guſts, and Breath of Satans Temptations be, yet if our nature were not of it ſelf ductile, and pliant, the world had never been ſo prodigiouſly toſſed up and down, nay, often overturned by erroneous Maximes. Now there are Two Principles in man, which are alwaies ſuſceptible of any falſe and Heretical Impreſſion; the one is, his <hi>Ignorance</hi> in ſpiritual mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, the other is, his <hi>Pride</hi> inNatural Knowledge. By his <hi>Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance,</hi> he is apt to miſtake Errour for truth, and by his <hi>Pride</hi> he is apt to propagate it; that like <hi>Simon Magus</hi> (the firſt noted Heretick in the Church of Chriſt) he may appear <hi>ſome body</hi> in the eyes of a few partial Followers;
<note place="margin">Acts 8.</note> and this is it, which makes his <hi>Errour Hereſie.</hi> So that till we can find ſome Art to change the Nature of man, to make his <hi>Underſtanding</hi> more refined, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lime and ſpiritual; till we can purge the <hi>Will</hi> from prejudice, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign and partiality; till we can alter the courſe of his <hi>Affections;</hi> and ſet them afloat another way, to love God, in ſtead of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and to prefer Truth before applauſe; till we can do this, we have as little hope to ſee the Church free from <hi>Hereſies,</hi> as to have our Gardens clear from infectious Miſts and Vapours, which have the Sun to exhale, the wind to convey, and a Bog hard by, to ingender them.</p>
            <p>But beſides theſe <hi>Cauſes,</hi> which do abſolutely neceſſitate the <hi>Being</hi> of <hi>Hereſies.</hi> There are two other <hi>Occaſions,</hi> which do migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily conduce, if I may ſo ſpeak, to the <hi>well-being</hi> of them, <hi>i. e.</hi> to their eaſier growth and ſpreading. And they are, 1. <hi>Scripture<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>difficulty.</hi> 2. <hi>Chriſtian Liberty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Occaſion </seg>1</label> 1. The <hi>Difficulty of Scripture</hi> is a very great occaſion for the increaſe of <hi>Hereſies,</hi> becauſe of that variety of Interpretation, which many places, eſpecially in the Apoſtle <hi>Pauls</hi> Epiſtles, are capable of: Whoſe Writings, even in the Apoſtle <hi>Peters</hi> time, were liable to much miſſe-conſtruction. For to omit, that the things themſelves recorded by him,
<note place="margin">2 Pet. 3.</note> are <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ſoarcely intelligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,</hi> being full of myſterious and fathomleſs depths, they are written by that excellent Apoſtle, in a ſtyle ſo diſſonant from all Rules of ordinary Grammar, that it requires great pains, meerly to find out his Literal Meaning. Which Induſtry, very few, who read him with prepoſſeſſion and prejudice, have leiſure for; and therefore haſtily expound their own ſenſe, without attending to
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:62794:12"/>his: So that, as <hi>Tertullian</hi> obſerves,
<note place="margin">De Praeſcript. Haeretic.</note> God ſeems to have ordered the Text of Scripture on purpoſe, that it might afford opportunity to <hi>Heretical Gloſſes.</hi> For as in the works of Providence, though the whole Frame and Syſteme of the world be admirably well-compoſed, compoſed, yet, if we conſider them in patcels, we ſhall meet with many things, which will ſtartle us into jealous, and miſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believing Thoughts. So is it in that compleat body of Divine Truth contained in Scripture, the whole Connexion and Series, as it relates to the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> foretold in the Old, and fulfilled in the New Teſtament, together with thoſe raviſhing heights of Heavenly Directions for life, is moſt ineffably curious, and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent: But if we take thoſe things aſunder, and conſider them diſtinctly, by <hi>Chapter</hi> and <hi>Verſe,</hi> we ſhall meet with <hi>Miſtakes in Chronology, Variations in Names, Diverſity of Readings,</hi> and ſome leſſer ſeeming contradictions, which to a ſnarling and quarrelſom wit, are ſo many Bones, for him to ſpend his mouth upon, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out minding more wholſom and digeſtible Food. And yet this makes very much for the plauſible entrance of an <hi>Hereſie,</hi> that it hath the Letter of Scripture to countenance it: The <hi>Papiſt</hi> will urge for his <hi>Implicit Faith, Hear the Church,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 18.</note> without ever con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering, that by the <hi>Church</hi> there, is not meant, what he fancies, a <hi>Pope,</hi> or <hi>Cardinals,</hi> or <hi>Councils,</hi> or <hi>Fathers,</hi> but a <hi>Select Number of Chriſtians;</hi> which is the only ſenſe wherein that word <hi>Church</hi> is taken throughout the whole New Teſtament, when it is uſed by our Saviour and his Apoſtles. So the <hi>Socinian</hi> ſhelters his impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous denying of our Saviours Divine Nature, under that, which he finds our Saviour ſpeaking, <hi>The Father is greater then I:</hi> not conſidering in what capacity our Saviour ſpake theſe words, <hi>viz.</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 16.</note> according to the Perſon he then took; or how many other places there are, wherein his equality with the Father is aſſerted. The <hi>Arminian</hi> wants not the ſame Plauſibilities for his <hi>Free will:</hi> and in ſhort, no Hereſie that ever yet was in the Chriſtian world, but pleaded Scripture for its defence and Patronage; which ſuch ſtrange Variety of Opinions could never have done, were not the Scripture exceeding difficult and hard to be underſtood, and thereby an occaſion given for the Riſe and Conceiving of them.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Occaſion </seg>2</label> 2. The ſecond Occaſion of the large growth and ſpreading of Hereſies, is <hi>Christian Liberty:</hi> Which in no Religion is allowed,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:62794:13"/>nay commanded, in that Latitude, as in ours. For we are enjoyned to <hi>try all things,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Theſ. 5.21. 1 John 4.1. Cal. 1.8.</note> and then, <hi>to hold faſt that which is good:</hi> We are bid, <hi>to try the Spirits,</hi> and though <hi>an Angel ſhould come form Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> and preach to us, we are not to believe him, if he teach a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing <hi>contrary to this Goſpel.</hi> We are commanded to ſee with our own eyes, and to chuſe for our ſelves; without depending any further upon the Authority of <hi>Fathers</hi> and <hi>Doctors,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 8.20.</note> then as they ſpeak <hi>according to this word,</hi> which under the ſevereſt penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, we are obliged to ſtudy and peruſe. For as God, in the old Teſtament,
<note place="margin">Mal. 1.</note> 
               <hi>would not have the blind for ſacrifice,</hi> ſo neither will he in the New; and they had as good not worſhip him at all, who like the <hi>Samaritans,</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 4.</note> worſhip him they know not why. And as in point of <hi>Judgment,</hi> we are to be thus <hi>free;</hi> ſo likewiſe in point of Practiſe,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 7. Mat. 15. Gal. 5.1.</note> as to Religious <hi>Rites</hi> and <hi>Orders,</hi> we are commanded, not to be <hi>the ſervants of men;</hi> not <hi>to worſhip God by the Precepts of men;</hi> not <hi>to be entangled with any yoke of Bondage,</hi> but to <hi>ſtand faſt in the liberty wherewith Chriſt hath made us free;</hi>
               <note place="margin">James 1.1, 2.</note> Whereupon, our Goſpel is called the <hi>Royal Law of Liberty;</hi> and we are, <hi>ſo to ſpeak, and ſo to do, as thoſe that ſhall be judged by that Law.</hi> Yea, further, as we are to be thus free in our ſelves, ſo we are to be exceeding charitable and tender towards others, bearing with our weak bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren; and if they do but hold the <hi>Foundation of Faith and good works,</hi> to tolerate the <hi>Hay and Stubble,</hi> which they may build up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it. And the reaſon of this is, becauſe our Religion, as it ſprang from Heaven, ſo is it maintained from thence; as the Spirit of God did firſt diſcover, ſo doth it ſtill reveal it; and by a new and almighty Birth, of dead and ſinful men, make us Living and ſincere Chriſtians:
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 3.16.</note> Now where <hi>the Spirit of God is,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>there is Liberty, i. e.</hi> not only Freedom from Errour and Ignorance, of which he there ſpeaks, but from thoſe wretched and inhumane Acts of Force and Fraud, whereby other Political In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions, rather then Religions, are continued and upheld in the world: For whereas all others <hi>hate the Light,</hi> and will not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure to have their Principles queſtioned, as is clear in that devil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Cheat and <hi>Myſtery of Iniquity,</hi> the <hi>Papacy:</hi> Our Religion deſires nothing more, then to be ſifted to the bottom, that ſo it may be choſen, for its own native Truth and Excellency, and not for any outward Advantages, or to ſerve a State-turn, which Chriſtian Religion will never ſtoop to do. And whoever have
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:62794:13"/>not after the moſt ſerious ſtudy and impartial Examination, arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to an embracing of this <hi>Faith,</hi> muſt needs loſe the Comfort, Satiſfaction and Sweetneſs of it, becauſe till a man hath met with, and in his own mind reſolved all Objections that make againſt him, he cannot be certain that he is in the right, but muſt upon the riſing of every doubt, be full of anxious fear and perplexity. This which I have ſaid concerning the neceſſity of <hi>Chriſtian Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> doth by accident prove a great means for the propagating of <hi>Hereſies;</hi> for as where the Soyl is good, and the Ayr free and warm, Weeds will ſpring up as well as good Corn: So is it in the Church of Chriſt, ſince there is Liberty allowed for variety of Judgments, Errour muſt needs thrive and ſpread, as well as truth.
<note place="margin">Mat. 13.</note> Eſpecially ſince we may not pull up the <hi>Tares,</hi> or by the hand of violence, ſtop the Progreſs of the moſt deceitful Errour; but if <hi>ſound Perſwaſion,</hi> if <hi>Demonſtration of the Spirit and Scripture,</hi> if <hi>Rejecting of the Heretick,</hi> and <hi>forbearing of Communion with him,</hi> will not prevail, to make him renounce his Errour, I am not yet convinced, that in Opinions concerning Matters meerly ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, our Religion doth allow any other more offenſive weapons. So that ſince to that <hi>Liberty,</hi> which is given to the ſowing of <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies,</hi> there is added Impunity unto their growth and progreſs, it muſt needs follow, that the <hi>Cauſes</hi> I mentioned, do not more neceſſitate the Being of <hi>Hereſies,</hi> then theſe <hi>Occaſions</hi> will neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitate their Thriving and Continuance.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe </seg>1</label> 1. The Inference from hence ſhall be to teach us, not to miſtake the <hi>Occaſions of Hereſie,</hi> for the <hi>Cauſes</hi> of it. Among thoſe who are exact and critical Writers of Hiſtory, as <hi>Polybius, Tacitus,</hi> and others, we find, they diſtinguiſh carefully between the <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and the <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the <hi>Beginning,</hi> and the <hi>cauſes</hi> of a War. The <hi>Begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> of a War may ariſe from ſomthing apparent and viſible; whereas the <hi>cauſe</hi> of it may be more deeply laid, even concealed from the view of the Actors. So in this caſe, the <hi>Occaſions</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed of <hi>Hereſie,</hi> which do midwife it into the world, are <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture-difficulty,</hi> and <hi>chriſtian Liberty:</hi> Whereas the true <hi>cauſes</hi> are thoſe I have mentioned; eſpecially <hi>Man himſelf,</hi> whoſe Heart is the Womb, in which that evil Birth is formed. And therefore let us take heed that through haſt and prejudice, we ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe not either the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> or <hi>due Chriſtian Freedom,</hi> of thoſe Errours, which meerly our own Ignorance, Preſumption and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:62794:14"/>Partiality do produce. To accuſe the <hi>Scripture</hi> for our Hereſies, is all one as if, becauſe we meet with ill ſents, we ſhould blame the Sun, and not the Dunghil. So likewiſe, as to <hi>Liberty of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi> to charge that with the production of Errours, is all one, as if the Ayr without, rather then ill humours within us, ſhould be thought the cauſe of our Diſeaſes. Let wicked and light-ſpirited men then bear the blame of whatever Follies they hold; and not either the <hi>Reading of Scripture</hi> be diſgraced, without which, there can be no Knowledge of Truth: nor <hi>Liberty of Conſcience</hi> be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barred; without which, there can be no openneſs of Profeſſion; both which are as neceſſary to Chriſtian Faith, as the Sun and Ayr are to Natural Life, we cannot ſee without the one, nor breath without the other. Take away <hi>Scripture,</hi> and we are in this world as Mariners upon the Sea, without a Compaſs; who have nothing but the violence of waves, and the uncertain motion of the wind, to drive them. Deny <hi>Liberty,</hi> I mean, in things <hi>Lawful,</hi> then Chriſtian Prudence, Charity, condeſcention, and wiſe doing, or forbearing of things indifferent, as we ſee occaſion, lie all uſeleſs by us, and we labour to become more knowing then others, to no purpoſe.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe </seg>2</label> 2. Is it ſo neceſſary, that there muſt be <hi>hereſies,</hi> then let us not take offence, or think ever a whit the worſe of our Religion, for that great Variety of <hi>Hereſies</hi> which have ſprung up in our daies. When the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> was himſelf in trouble, he writes to the Church of <hi>Theſsalonica, That no man ſhould be moved by theſe affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions; for,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>your ſelves know, that we were appointed thereunto, for verily when we were with you,
<note place="margin">1 Theſ. 3, 3, 4.</note> we told you before, that we ſhould ſuffer Tribulation, even as it came to paſs.</hi> If they were to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted under their <hi>Afflictions,</hi> becauſe he foretold them, we have the ſame reaſon to be comforted under our <hi>Hereſies,</hi> ſince he foretold them too; and from thence hath afforded us an excellent Argument, to aſſert our Saviours Truth and Veracity, and in that, the Truth of our Religion, againſt all Oppoſers. This uſe the Primitive Writers made of them, when <hi>Celſus</hi> and others did object to the Chriſtians, the great variety of Opinions, and diverſity of Judgments amongſt them, ſo that, ſay they, <hi>Were we willing to turn Chriſtians, we know not of what Party to be, ſince not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding your Feuds and Quarrels, you all equally pretend to Chriſt.</hi> To this, <hi>Tertullian, Origen,</hi> and the reſt reply, <hi>Haereſes
<pb facs="tcp:62794:14"/>non dolemus veniſſe, quiae novimus eſſe praedictas. WE are not at all ſorry, that Hereſies are come, for we knew it was foretold they ſhould come.</hi> So that the very Argument, which the Heathens uſed to diſgrace Chriſtianity, was by thoſe wiſe and Learned men im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved for the Illuſtration and confirming of it: And, indeed, ſince, as I have already demonſtrated,
<note place="margin">Demonſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that Jeſus is the Chriſt.</note> there cannot be a more ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Proof of the Divine Miſſion of any, then the <hi>fulfilling of his Propheſies,</hi> it is very admirable to conſider, how our Saviour hath left ſuch Predictions behind him; which were beyond any Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Foreſight, and yet every Age hath been fulfilling ſome or other of them, ever ſince his time. That a Religion ſo harmleſs, and inoffenſive, ſhould be perſecuted: that notwithſtanding per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution, it ſhould take root, and be preached throughout the world: That preſently after it was propagated, there ſhould be <hi>Sects</hi> and <hi>Hereſies</hi> formed out of it; and this to be the conſtant, un-erring Fate of our Religion, was a thing beyond all Rational and meerly humane Conjecture; and therefore the fulfilling of this great Prediction concerning <hi>Hereſies,</hi> ſhould make us with thankfulneſs look up to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> who hath already armed us againſt any Prejudice we may receive from them, ſince they are only diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coveries of his Truth, and Trials of ours.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe </seg>3</label> But yet, Thirdly and Laſtly, Let no man think, that becauſe <hi>Hereſies</hi> are <hi>neceſſary,</hi> that therefore any ſhall be excuſed, who is the Author of them; Hereſies are no otherwiſe neceſſary, then <hi>Scandals</hi> and <hi>Sins</hi> are, of which, our Saviour ſaith, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>they muſt be; but yet,</hi> ſaies he, <hi>Wo be to that man by whom they come.
<note place="margin">Mat. 18. Rom. 16.17.</note> Mark them,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle <hi>Paul, which cauſe Diviſions and Offences, contrary to the Doctrine which ye have received, and avoid them.</hi> And in another place, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>The Sect-making man, after the firſt and ſecond Admonition, reject;
<note place="margin">Tit. 3. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> knowing that ſuch a one is quite perverted, and ſins, being ſelf-condemned.</hi> All which Places, with many other, making ſo directly againſt new-fang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledneſs of Opinion, I cannot but wonder at the boldneſs of thoſe men, who are not content only to ſtart up new and needleſs O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions, but to the diſhonour of our Religion, and their own Eternal Ruine, if they repent not, make thoſe Opinions the Grounds of <hi>Separation</hi> from all Church-Aſſemblies, but their own. Whoever doth thus ſet up for himſelf, muſt be able to demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate theſe Three things. 1. That the Opinion he diſſents from,
<pb facs="tcp:62794:15"/>is apparently falſe and damnable. 2. That the Opinion he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf holds, is certainly and infallibly true. 3. That it is abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely unlawful for him to joyn in communion with another, who in that particular (as for inſtance, in <hi>Infant-Baptiſm</hi>) differs in Judgment from him. The two firſt of which Aſſertions, very ſew of our <hi>Separate Churches</hi> will be able to maintain, and I am ſure, the laſt, none can. For if the Errour of another be not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed upon my Practiſe, I ought not to withdraw my ſelf from the Communion of any, who hold the Foundation of Chriſtian Faith, namely, <hi>Belief in Jeſus being the Christ;</hi> as is clear in the practiſe of theſe <hi>Corinthians,</hi> among whom, ſome denied the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection,</hi> and yet were all preſent at the ſame Sacrament. This Doctrine, becauſe it ſtrikes at the Root of all Separation, which cannot be juſtified, but in caſe of indiſpenſable neceſſity, <hi>viz.</hi> when ſuch things are impoſed upon us, as Conditions of Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, which we cannot in Conſcience ſubmit to; for there if we depart, we do not go, but are driven out. But this deſerves to be more largely handled; which I ſhall reſerve for a particular Treatiſe.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
